<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vaishnavh Nagarajan</title>
    <description>Welcome to my personal website!</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Angles between high-dimensional vectors</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Switch off your brain and answer this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Given three points $\mathbf{X}, \mathbf{Y}, \mathbf{Z}$ sampled from a high-dimensional zero-centered isotropic Gaussian $\mathcal{N}(0, \mathbf{\Sigma})$, roughly, what is the angle between the lines given by $\mathbf{A} = \mathbf{X} - \mathbf{Y}$ and $\mathbf{B} = \mathbf{Z} - \mathbf{Y}$?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2025-12-16-high-dimensional-diff/img1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The question&quot; class=&quot;theme-aware-img center-image img-rounded&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you answered &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot; onclick=&quot;this.classList.toggle(&apos;revealed&apos;)&quot; title=&quot;Click to reveal&quot;&gt;
  $90^\circ$
&lt;/span&gt;, that is not right. 
The right answer is in fact, a cute yet shocking&lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot; onclick=&quot;this.classList.toggle(&apos;revealed&apos;)&quot; title=&quot;Click to reveal&quot;&gt;
  $60^\circ$
&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s entrenched in us that everything becomes funny in high-dimensions, and one such funny thing we know all too well is that &lt;em&gt;if you independently sample two vectors from a zero-centered, isotropic Gaussian, they must be at right angles&lt;/em&gt; (with high probability etc., etc.,). We sense that the two directions ($\mathbf{A}$ and $\mathbf{B}$) look just like two zero-centered, isotropic Gaussian directions—which they are—and by our funny law, they should be orthogonal to each other—which they are not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is joy in trying to reconcile this from various angles; try it yourself before you read below. The process of reconciliation also generated some philosophical mumblings; I leave them at the end of the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-algebraic-reconciliation&quot;&gt;The algebraic reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a blunt reconciliation, I go through the motions of computing the expected dot-product of $\mathbf{A} \cdot \mathbf{B}$ as below,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(\require{cancel} \mathbb{E}[ (\mathbf{X} - \mathbf{Y})\cdot (\mathbf{Z} - \mathbf{Y})] = \cancelto{0}{\mathbb{E}[\mathbf{X}\cdot\mathbf{Z}]} + \cancelto{0}{\mathbb{E}[\mathbf{Y}\cdot\mathbf{Z}]} + \cancelto{0}{\mathbb{E}[\mathbf{X}\cdot\mathbf{Y}]} + \underbrace{\mathbb{E}[\mathbf{Y}\cdot\mathbf{Y}]}_{&amp;gt; 0}\),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and I find that things don’t cancel out to zero! Thus, the angle cannot concentrate around $90^\circ$. But I find this argument too robotic to be insightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-statistical-reconciliation&quot;&gt;The statistical reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, I could say that my folly was in treating the two quantities, $\mathbf{A}$ and  $\mathbf{B}$ as two &lt;em&gt;independent&lt;/em&gt;  zero-centered Gaussian random variables. Zero-centered Gaussian they are, independent they are not: the presence of “$\mathbf{Y}$” in both terms spoils the relationship. Knowing $\mathbf{A}$ i.e., $\mathbf{X}-\mathbf{Y}$ gives me an updated belief over  where $\mathbf{Z} - \mathbf{Y}$ i.e., $\mathbf{B}$ could be.
 Therefore, I can’t cite the funny law of high-dimensional-orthogonality here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I find this argument too bureaucratic to be insightful. (“You broke this precondition, so this claim cannot be processed.” Why, thank you, insurance agent!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-other-statistical-reconciliation&quot;&gt;The other statistical reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me freeze $\mathbf{Y}$ at some specific value $\mathbf{y}$. &lt;em&gt;Conditioned&lt;/em&gt; on $\mathbf{Y}=\mathbf{y}$, I think about what the angle between $\mathbf{X}-\mathbf{y}$ and $\mathbf{Z}-\mathbf{y}$ concentrates towards. Under this conditioning, I see that although these variables are independent, they are &lt;em&gt;no longer&lt;/em&gt; zero-centered Gaussian: they have mean $\mathbf{y}$. Once again, I am mysteriously blocked from citing the funny high-dimensional law, this time by a different force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-frame-of-reference-reconciliation&quot;&gt;The frame-of-reference reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the above statistical arguments can in fact be expressed more vividly. What I did right above was to move my frame of reference to the “$\mathbf{y}$”. By relabeling “$\mathbf{y}$” as my new origin $\mathbf{O}’$ (see image below), what were once the points $\mathbf{X}$ and $\mathbf{Z}$, are now points $\mathbf{A}$ and $\mathbf{B}$. These points are sampled from a far-off Gaussian galaxy that is centered at $-\mathbf{y}$; not centered around me! So, from my planet at $\mathbf{y}$, the directions $\mathbf{A}$ and $\mathbf{B}$ appear in the sky roughly
in the direction of that galaxy; not at right angles. 
In this universe, you can also “see” how knowing where $\mathbf{A}$ is, gives you an updated belief over where $\mathbf{B}$ is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, this is also what the “algebraic reconciliation” was trying to tell me when it spat out $\mathbb{E}[(-\mathbf{Y}) \cdot (-\mathbf{Y})]$ as the dot-product $\mathbb{E}[\mathbf{A} \cdot \mathbf{B}]$. Sadly, this is robotic garble I couldn’t parse then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2025-12-16-high-dimensional-diff/img2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame-of-reference reconciliation&quot; class=&quot;theme-aware-img center-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 60%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-geometric-reconciliation&quot;&gt;The geometric reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there’s one more elegant visualization. We can legally cite a different funny law in high-dimensions: the distances between two random points from a Gaussian concentrate around a fixed value. This value doesn’t matter. All that matters is that this is true of the distances between every pair of $\mathbf{X}, \mathbf{Y} \; \&amp;amp; \; \mathbf{Z}$, which means  these points together form a delightful equilateral triangle. QED.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2025-12-16-high-dimensional-diff/img3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Geometric reconciliation&quot; class=&quot;theme-aware-img center-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 30%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When our gut feeling says that the angle was $90^\circ$, were we tricked by the deceptive nature of high-dimensions, or were we tricked by something more rudimentary? (I think it’s the latter.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When we learn a new thing,
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we examine the thing from various angles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we examine every existing intuition in our head that is at odds with the thing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;and we work until all possible contradictions are reconciled;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;only then does the thing become a part of our world view without resistance; only then do we feel like we understood the thing to completion.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a useful exercise to “shut one’s brain” and see where it goes right or wrong. Don’t think step by step.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t feel like I learned something satisfyingly without the aid of visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How much of AI model training reflects the above two human ways of incorporating new knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What does it really mean to explain something?&lt;/em&gt; The algebraic reconciliation explains little. It is somewhat analogous to proving a generalization guarantee for a deep network with a 100-page step-by-step analysis of each layer when trained on a Gaussian distribution — does it really explain generalization of overparameterized models? In the 1970s, when Appel and Haken gave their computer-aided proof for the four-color theorem, there was criticism from mathematicians. It was not aesthetic; the computer-generated part of the proof allegedly was a “four-foot-high computer printout”; one couldn’t glean high-level arguments or insights into the “why” behind the truth; in fact, one couldn’t even verify and convince themselves of the truth without spending astronomical amounts of time. Jim Holt writes about this in a beautiful essay, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nybooks.com/articles/2003/05/29/a-comedy-of-colors/&quot;&gt;“A Comedy of Colors”&lt;/a&gt;, asking what makes a proof a proof.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/high-dimensional-diff/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/high-dimensional-diff/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research philosophy</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I pompously share my thoughts on how I aspire to be a researcher. My hope is that junior researchers who hold similar ideas and have faced the challenges that come with holding them, feel some sense of support from reading this. I’m always happy to chat more about navigating these challenges amidst the rat race that is AI/ML research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I seek simple, insightful results unburdened by mathematical obfuscation. This means pursuing minimal abstractions, example and counterexamples, vivid intuition, clarity and depth of thought and nuanced argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers should be publishing significantly less. In the first ten years of my career (2015 to 2025, the date I write this) I have published about a paper a year&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:author&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:author&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,  I wish it was less frequent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Peer review is a form of taxation. If you publish more, you should review more, while ensuring that your reviews are of high quality. The System Is Broken™ in part because everyone’s publishing more without paying their fair share of taxes (and also because there’s more of everyone).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I care about clear and accessible communication. I enjoy spending an unhealthy amount of time on making my &lt;a href=&quot;/talks&quot;&gt;talks&lt;/a&gt; and writing my papers. This is a constant learning process—every paper or talk takes at least two or three attempts to attain clear presentation. There is significant insight to be  derived from this process.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I enjoy the detective work that goes behind cataloging an extensive, well-organized related work section. It’s a satisfying process. If there are missing citations in my work, please reach out to me so I can rectify it. Again, there is significant insight (and knowledge) to be derived from this process!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I  believe that science must be done and truth must be sought collaboratively with compassion and good faith, building on each other’s works and strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Science is more subjective than it is made out to be. We must embrace this with humility. It’s not always obvious what questions are important, or what directions will be fruitful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point in my field, the only form of external validation that matters to me is when others tangibly build on my work, or if someone enjoyed reading my work. All other metrics (including citations, publications, awards, talk invitations and fellowships I’ve listed elsewhere on this site) have become utterly meaningless.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Byte-sized dissemination of research on twitter has been a terrible idea for science (but I do it anyway). It has encouraged reductive and combative interactions. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My values are shaped by what I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/history-of-science/&quot;&gt;read&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Footnotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:author&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As lead contributor or mentor. As I grew in seniority, I’ve additionally participated as a “middle author” in about a paper a year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:author&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, that’s hypocritical! But also see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tu_quoque&quot;&gt;Tu quoque&lt;/a&gt; fallacy. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/research-philosophy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/research-philosophy/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why PhD students should read the history of science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s a secret I accidentally discovered during my PhD: consuming history-of-science content is a powerful way to nurture your emotional maturity as a researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice, even as you read two random pages from the history of science, the pages have an uncanny resemblance to each other, and to the one you’re writing! Every tale of discovery demonstrates that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scientists always gambled in the scientific process, and made mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Science is noisy and subjective. There can be great subjectivity in interpreting a result or appreciating the significance of a direction. The subjectivity may disappear only in hindsight with more data and more exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lesser-known scientists were rarely taken seriously, especially by scientists who were backed by reputation or seniority or systemic power or mere confidence. There were always pushbacks, humiliations, and complete indifference.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Controversies between scientists has always been the norm. “Big and proud” personalities in power have made other scientists’ lives miserable. Or at times, two “big” scientists on an equal footing sparred publicly with each other. It wasn’t very nice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Credit assignment has always been noisy and at other times, deliberately unfair. Some great scientific discoveries were tragically known only long after their originator’s passing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are important lessons in these observations&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that make you a more level-headed and emotionally mature researcher.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You learn to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;recognize the inevitable ups and downs of the research process,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;navigate the terrain of research with grit,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;value deeply satisfying long-term ambitions over anxiety-inducing short-term goals,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;value goal-less, curiosity-driven random explorations as an exciting and important part of working at the frontier of human knowledge,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;not perceive certain setbacks or the lack of external validation as a personal attack in those situations where it is not personal but pure noise (not always the case!),&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;not be intimidated by those who may assert their subjective opinions as objective truth with authority (this is my favorite lesson),&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;hold on to a measured conviction in your own opinions (second favorite lesson).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these lessons&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; may sound like platitudes; but learning how these have repeatedly manifested in history — through vivid narrative detail — leaves a profound imprint on how you operate as a researcher, and how you construct an inner narrative about your role in the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I contend that you cannot learn this emotional maturity efficiently through the brute-force of the research process alone. You need to read.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-list&quot;&gt;Reading list&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the books I would recommend. I’ll continue to update this over time. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Longitude&lt;/strong&gt; by Dava Sobel&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This little book describes the story of how 18th century governments and monarchies funded a race to design the clock, a race that stemmed from colonial ambitions (you need clocks to track the longitude which until then was extremely cumbersome and prone to ship-wrecking errors). The book covers the competition and drama that ensued between inventors and powerful astronomers and the magnitude of grit that was involved in the inventor&apos;s process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chaos: Making a New Science&lt;/strong&gt; by James Gleick&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This narrates the emergence of Chaos Theory as a standalone discipline (born from problems and observations in various other disciplines) and the pushbacks it experienced along the way. The book also describes the basic tenets of chaos theory in a way that is easy to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chasing Venus: The Race to Measure the Heavens&lt;/strong&gt; by Andrea Wulf&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This thriller-like (true) story tracks the journey of a dozen astronomers (of many) in the 1760s as they raced to colonies in various corners of the globe. Their goal was to time the journey of the Venus across the Sun in a bid to measure the distance of the Sun from the Earth. The scientists and astronomers worked across imperial borders to consolidate resources and collaborate (or not!), and in their race against time, they faced one obstacle after another, political, logistical and meteorological. Many failed. The book details the competition that developed between various astronomers (and like Longitude, also how all of this was deeply tied to colonization).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Great Feuds in Science: Ten of the Liveliest Disputes Ever&lt;/strong&gt; by Hal Hellman&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This outlines instances across the vast history of science where two ideas or two people collided head-on. Some of these you may already be aware of, like the one between Newton and Leibniz or the one between Galileo and the Pope. But the book digs out little historical details which paint a picture of many of these debates nastier than what you’d have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When Einstein Walked with Gödel&lt;/strong&gt; by Jim Holt&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A collection of essays on science and mathematics, each with a unique insight into some of the lessons I brought up earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accidental Astronomy: How Random Discoveries Shape the Science of Space&lt;/strong&gt; by Chris Lintott&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This describes the serendipitous history leading up to many astronomical discoveries. The story of how radio astronomy came to be is absolutely fascinating. The book also led me to learning about the story of Jocelyn Bell who discovered the  pulsars but was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenews.org/article/jocelyn-bell-burnell-physics-prize-pulsar-discovery-interview&quot;&gt;not awarded&lt;/a&gt; the Nobel Prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Creative Moment&lt;/strong&gt; by Joseph Schwartz&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; A collection of (provocative) essays describing how various scientific discoveries were triggered by a political or social force; and also, how the natural sciences became more and more abstract and obscured in the public eye (beginning at the moment Galileo mathematized physics when in conflict with the Church), and how the ways of doing science have transformed from lone inventors to large highly-managed teams, a fact that is true of machine learning and AI too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inventing Temperature&lt;/strong&gt; by Hasok Chang&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This narrates the long history behind how temperature began to measured like how it is right now. There are details about the physics of it (some of it was a bit dense for a casual read for me), but also details about the disputes and confusion that transpired along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are places in the world where rules are less important than kindness&lt;/strong&gt; by Carlo Rovelli&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A collection of essays by a theoretical physicist that touches upon many things broadly: science, anthropology, also of the life of a young scientist, and of many other social and human values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A sense of the mysterious&lt;/strong&gt; by Alan Lightman&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; The essays here describe the emotional experience of a scientist and the intersection of being scientist and an artist (Alan’s writing about this is beautiful; it deeply resonated with me) and the power of metaphors in scientific thinking. There are also insightful historical accounts of some scientists and discoveries; my favorite is the essay titled “Megaton Man” which descibes the personality of Edward Teller who was involved in the Manhattan Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science and Government&lt;/strong&gt; by CP Snow&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; A long essay (or a short book?) that narrates the rivalry between two scientists who were at the helm of British military technology during the second World War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Knowledge Machine&lt;/strong&gt; by Michael Strevens&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This book presents a theory of why science emerged when it did; what stood out to me are examples of scientists making irrational or un-objective decisions e.g., such as in the Eddington eclipse experiment where scientists ignored some data that might have otherwise tipped the scales in favor of Newton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received a few more suggestions from readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ascent of Man&lt;/strong&gt; by Bronowski  (h/t Tarun Gupta)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infinite Powers&lt;/strong&gt; by Steven Strogatz (h/t Puneesh Deora)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Emergence of Probability&lt;/strong&gt; by Ian Hacking and &lt;strong&gt;Science in history&lt;/strong&gt; by Bernal (h/t Javier Burroni)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Footnotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While point 1 and 2 are inherent to science and research, the rest are idiosyncrasies of the current system of doing science. It does not have to be this way and I do not mean to normalize any of it, and I truly wish they were gone. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There is another important dynamic you’ll notice in history, one which is less personal and more social:   science has interacted with politics in unfortunate and devastating ways causing great and unequal harms. This interaction goes in two ways. Science creates new political tension, and conversely, political tension both hastens and hinders science. This is a topic of its own and is important to pay attention to while you read! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most of these books are random picks from various old book stores, so they do not come vetted by popularity. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My summaries are based off of memory so please actually read the book. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/history-of-science/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/history-of-science/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>